this is Luke Marsden from HelixML.
He's going to be talking to us about giving every agent its own desktop
lessons from dogfooding. Helix ML.
Thank you very much.
Thank you. Cool.
Everyone.
It's nice to be here. Yeah.
I'm going to talk about basically how we use agents ourselves
and things that we built to do it better.
So just to introduce myself.
I'm Luke.
I self-identify as a kind human.
I'm also the CEO at Helix where we do private agents.
And before that I didn't MLOps business.
I was cluster lifecycle lead for the Kubernetes project,
and I also did a DevOps company doing storage for Docker
and Kubernetes back in the early Docker and Kubernetes days.
So so my thesis is that all information
work is eventually going to become about managing agents.
And it's just software engineering where that's really started.
And it's kind of makes sense
why it started in software engineering because that's also where AI came from.
But eventually
everyone who is moving information around in any way,
basically all white collar workers are going to end up having to interact
with with agents one way or another.
It's a bit difficult to see on this slide, but this is from Steve.
Yeah, who is the creator of Gastown.
And he talks about how
there are these different stages of AI adoption that people go through.
And you go from just kind of using
chat completion like a GitHub copilot through to running
like a single CLI agent, like a Claude code.
And then you kind of get
bored of babysitting a single agent running on your computer,
at which point
you're like, oh,
I should be able to go faster if I run more than one of these in parallel.
And that's where the problems start, because the naive approach to
that is just run many agents on the same working directory,
and then you end up in the horrible situations.
Like when I was rushing to prepare a presentation for a customer in Paris,
and I was up early on a Monday morning and I was trying to get my
I was trying to run five agents in parallel to get everything done,
and one of them decided to get stashed the work
that all the other ones were doing.
And then the following day, a different agent decided
to RF dot on my git checkout.
And this actually happened.
So I've been working since 2023
on making it possible to run agents
and LMS and Rag and all that stuff around it
that that runs entirely on your own infrastructure.
And we've been working with, with people who who care about that.
And so kind of late last year, I got really obsessed with this idea
of making the snake eats its own tail
by actually using our own stuff that we were building to build itself.
And, and so we, we also were lucky to have customers who,
who wanted to push us towards the sort of coding
agent side of, of the equation.
And so we've spent a lot of time
thinking about kind of this design space for systems
that run agents and in particular systems that, that run agents on the server.
So all I want to say here is
and we'll go through each of these in turn in the slides.
Kind of warning contains opinions.
And the reason I'm sharing these opinions is that I hope
they will be helpful to anyone else who's building systems like this.
So kind of both lay out kind of the shape of the landscape,
and then also carve out some specific opinions,
but also why I came to have them, because you might have different opinions
or you might not have thought about some of these things. So
the first big
decision in my opinion, is do you want to carry on
letting every developer run whatever agent they like, or maybe the
the same agent that everyone uses in the company,
but on their own specific development environment?
That's kind of like a snowflake.
Or do you want to create a pool of
agents that run on your organization's infrastructure
that many humans can interact with?
And my strong argument is that.
Going for the centralized approach and I say centralized,
it doesn't mean you have to
hand over all your data to OpenAI or run on their infrastructure or anything.
You can run it on your own infrastructure.
Still on Kubernetes or something, but there are
some significant benefits from having a centralized approach.
For example, you can have a globally distributed team
all around the world, and you can say
that when the sun sets in Tokyo and rises in London,
whoever a different human can carry on doing the work
that a certain agent was working on, especially if that agent truly
has its own computer for that specific task.
And so there's a really nice
article written by by someone.
We've been working with a company called DevIcon,
and what they said was, to be honest, agents, coding is not new.
Going from doing it the easier way, which is the way on the left
which is unsafe and per engineer to something global per company
and safe is is what they found interesting in this approach.
So that's kind of my argument.
My opinion number one is
you should
give each agent their own computer, not each human.
It's almost like you wouldn't hire
a team of software developers and ask them all to share one computer.
You should give each agent their own computer.
The next opinion that I've come to is do.
Do we still need an ID?
Claude code started making us, like, not look at the code so much,
and I genuinely feel like it made me stupider.
My opinion is that you should still have an ID.
These agents will increasingly do
more autonomous, long running tasks.
But when it comes to actually stepping in and pair
programing with an agent, you do still need to be able
to look at the code, and having a visual display
that follows what the agent is doing is actually really useful
when you want to understand what it's doing.
Another thing that really matters is that things have to be fast.
I got incredibly frustrated with with cursor were back when I was a cursor user,
and just how slow it was at Hadley keyboard input.
And then Claude code came out with anthropic, came up with Claude code.
And they just do you know Claude code is implemented in react.
And so they've ended up having to implement
basically a web browser in the terminal.
And it's just like, can't we just have a working text box?
So anyway, the next thing I want to talk about is
how you organize your agents.
And there's kind of two different schools of thought here.
The first one is do you scale your agents out by number of tasks,
or do you try and build like an organization out of your agents,
and you hire a CEO agent
and they hire a VP of engineering agent, and the VP of engineering
agent hires some engineers and you give them all names or something.
And we are.
We started with the left hand approach because it's easier, but
we're researching the right hand approach.
But so far what we've researched, what we've found in the research
is if you go to fine grained on giving each agent their own
specific role and you give them these special channels they can communicate on,
like Agent Slack or something, they end up
kind of devolving into enterprise politics.
Because they were trained on
all of this human data of how humans argue with each other about stupid stuff.
So you end up burning a lot of tokens like that.
But what I, what I actually think is ultimately going to be appropriate
here is to combine the models where the
you have these coarse grained, different categorizations of roles
like marketing agents and sales agents and engineering agents,
because they all need different tools and connectivity to different systems.
But within those you scale the tasks, scale the agents by task.
So you have a sort of pool of of bees maybe, and so on.
So yeah, I also wanted to share some kind of demos
as I go to to illustrate the design decisions I'm talking about.
So I'll start with this one.
So what we put together here,
this is basically this idea of scaling by by task.
And the notion there is that
Kanban is quite a natural fit for scaling by task, because you want to
constrain the parallelism. So you can kick off.
This is a sample project that has a to do list app.
And what you can see hopefully, is that
by clicking play on the backlog, we've spun up three separate computers.
For those three agents that are working on those three different tasks.
One of them is adding a dark mode toggle.
Another one of them is fixing a bug.
Another one is adding like customized categories.
And so what you can see here is that we've gone
we ended up down this sort of rabbit
hole of like, okay, if you've got
if you want like a good background agent experience
that feels like a foreground agent experience,
you end up implementing GPU accelerated desktops
because non GPU accelerated desktops are not very nice to use.
But if we're doing AI infrastructure, we've got some GPUs lying around.
And it just so happens that the same GPUs are used for inference.
A lot of them also support
like what GPUs were originally for which is graphics,
and they also support hardware video encoding.
So we borrowed a lot of the technology from the gaming industry.
I don't know if anyone's ever played like
computer games in the cloud.
It's actually possible to get pretty low latency and good performance.
So so we're using the same the same tech as that.
But basically what's happening here from a process perspective
is the agent has.
Started up inside the IDE.
We use Zed because it's fast.
And we also forked it so that you can remote control it.
So we can inject prompts into the Zed agent.
And the other thing that's nice about Z is that it supports ACP,
which means it integrates with all of the major agent harnesses.
So it works with Codex and Claude code.
We're not trying to reinvent that bill
then.
Yeah.
So the next thing is like, well, what's that agent actually going to do
when it starts up?
And this is a Tessl conference.
So it would be bad not to talk about spec-driven development,
but I'm actually a huge fan of spec driven development.
So the approach that we've taken is.
Spec is central to to what's going on.
The the human prompt
that comes in is something really short, like add dark mode
support to my to do list app or something kind of really trivial.
And that prompt goes into the into this agent.
It's actually the same agent.
It's just the agent has an explicit planning phase and later
in implementation phase.
So we prompt the agent to say please write a plan.
Because it turns out that
if you get the agent to write a plan before it does the work, you get much,
much better results because you can then correct it and you can kind of
do that design work before the agent has gone off
in the wrong direction, when it's harder to steer it,
if it's in the middle of doing an implementation
and it's got it's misunderstood, something fundamental.
So you put the prompt in into the planning phase,
and then you have a human in the loop commenting, which you'll see in a second.
And then but, but the spec is the combination
of the human prompt and the planning agent reading the code.
So I don't know if you can see this red arrow here.
We've got a code
check out for the project, which is whatever repos you've attached.
And the job of the planning phase is based on the user's requirement.
Write a good spec based on also looking at the code,
so that you understand what you're going to do
in quite a lot more detail than the user specified.
And then once you approve the spec.
So there's a human human in the loop.
On commenting on the spec,
there's also a human in the loop on approving spec
to say, yes, I'm happy with that spec.
Then you go into the implementation phase and because each agent
has its own desktop environment, you can now do some interesting things
like the agent can self if it's a web application.
And lots and lots of things are web applications.
So you can then have the agent put up a PR on GitHub,
but then also kind of human in the loop review both the PR
but also the running application in that agents own computer.
And because each agent has its own isolated computer, they're actually
Docker and Docker environments or Docker on Kubernetes environments.
They can they're not treading on each other's toes when
they're bringing up a Chrome instance and using Chrome MCP to navigate around.
So yeah, I'll show you this.
Spec review phase.
So here we had these three tasks or four tasks.
And like a 30s a minute later
the systems created each agent has created its own spec.
And so if we go and look at the bug where deleting
a to do item from the to do list doesn't.
Doesn't delete it from from storage,
what you can see is it's come up with this spec.
So it was given that simple prompt.
There's a bug with deletion and it's come
and written out a much more detailed document.
And then you can comment on the document, because I believe that the terminal like
called code is actually a terrible place for reviewing and commenting on documents.
It's much nicer to use a Google Doc style UI, which is why we added one.
So you can see there's this kind of wrapper around
the agent where
you can comment on a line on the document, and it will push changes to the spec.
And the specs are all just markdown files in in a git repo.
And we put all those markdown files on a special branch that's separate
from the rest of the repo, so all the agents can see
all the other specs that all the other agents are working on.
So they're pretty isolated from each other,
but they can all see the history of all the work that's, that's happened
or, or is or, or is happening.
So then.
We fast forward this a little bit.
And what I did was I added a request to on deletion.
Let's also do like a fiery CSS animation.
So it looks like the to do list item is burning.
And then I can review the rest of the plan.
There's a basic to do list and then that's the human approval gate.
You click Approve Design.
And again we put the prompt in there.
And then I sped up the actual implementation part.
So I've only got 15 minutes left.
But then you can see this is the really cool part.
The agent starts shaping the application.
I'm not typing here.
The agent is typing by groceries and walk the dog and then watch.
It's going to delete by groceries I think.
And then we get to see the
animation and I'm like, that wasn't a very good fire animation.
So I'm going to prompt it and I'm going to say that was a bit rubbish.
I want to I want you to make it look like it was actually burning
in hell, as I think the phrase I used earlier.
So as soon as we
yeah, the CSS animation was not cool enough.
And then you can press enter twice
and it will interrupt the agent that's running in the background.
So it does some thinking
it comes up with with some better CSS animation.
And then you can kind of collaboratively QA
what the agent has done directly in the browser.
And it's pretty cool.
So it's actually kind of nice to give each agent their own computer
and to have a high quality,
like way of interacting with it that you'd actually want to use.
And just to give you a sense of what the board looks like after this,
you get to see that you've still got these items
to review the spec on, but then you've got this in progress task over here.
So there's a few other things that we learned from
kind of the change that the changes that come about
when instead of developers wanting to spend
all of their time looking at their ID to only leading to interact
with each agent like for a few minutes every hour, of course they can parallelize
and like try and try and do more, but
they can also go to the gym and
do some
exercise while their agents are doing work.
And so we also wanted to optimize for mobile experience.
So we made sure that
everything worked on
on mobile and on tablet.
I had I put a LinkedIn message out that was like our niche pitch is that
this is the best way to run
to to run Zed on your iPad while you're at the gym.
And I had one person commenting that was like, I feel seen.
So I guess that's our target audience.
But anyway, so the other interesting thing about this
is that notice this diagram, I had many users
looking at the same screen or many users looking at the same agent.
And so we added this kind of Figma like ability to have multiple mouse cursors.
And so you can actually start collaboratively
like multiple humans can basically pair on the same agents desktop.
And they can join in and they can they can both interact with it.
And one of those humans might be at the gym on their iPhone.
Anyway,
I'll go quickly.
The next thing that we found was really important
and actually stopped us using it.
Remember I was saying we wanted to have the snake eat its own tail.
We wanted to dog through this to make it build itself.
The next pain point we hit was it takes 20.
Sorry, it took 40 minutes to build our stack from scratch in Docker,
and there's really no point being able to spawn
agent sandboxes rapidly if those agents are going to take
40 minutes before they can do any useful work,
because they actually want to be able
to test and QA the application that they're changing themselves.
So we did some quite interesting things
with with ZFS as a filesystem
to make clones of the most development environments are in Docker.
That's our kind of working assumption. And
Doctor and Docker can
actually go 16 levels deep, which is crazy.
But we don't go 16, but we go like I think three.
But that means that you can give each agent its own Docker environment,
but we also prime the data directory in that Docker environment
with the latest version of the startup script running
against the latest main commit.
So every time an agent starts up, it's got a really fresh,
fully cached Docker environment to start up from.
And so this is how we use
this, how we use helix to build helix.
So here we've got an example of
a task I added which was can you review this external contribution.
We had
another
like lots of other tasks that are in progress
like we're doing notion integration for one user.
The desktops shut themselves down after an hour of being idle.
So I can start this one back up and then interact with it.
And I think I speed up the video here.
But basically everything we do now is done inside the tool.
And so we've achieved that goal of kind of the snake eating its own tail.
And most of my day now when I'm doing technical work
is that I'm reviewing these specs, and I find the two lines in the spec
where the agent got it wrong, or is making a poor design decision, or
is unaware of some other area of the code, and you just comment on those two lines,
and then it then becomes fairly mechanical
for the agent to get the code change all the way through to
to being close to being ready to merge.
So and then the pull requests that come out of it are quite nice,
because we put quite a lot of effort into telling the agent
to take screenshots of changes that it's made.
So I quite often review pull requests
now by just looking at whether I like the change.
And that's quite powerful.
And you can also link, we also link automatically to the spec
that was used to to construct it.
Now I want to talk briefly about token costs, privacy and Donald Trump.
The total costs are exploding.
We spent a lot of money now on tokens,
which as a bootstrap startup is kind of painful.
But we also have one of these machines,
these open weights models like GLM 5.1 and so on, and can now
do pretty much 80% of the work that you need to do.
And so
if you
take as a meaningfully sized organization kind of your next three month
token budget and instead invest in some hardware with like eight
RTX six K pros in it, and then you use something
or you build something that allows you
to easily switch between different agents and different models.
Then you can avoid getting locked into, like the OpenAI anthropic ecosystem,
but you can still kind of burst out to like Claude
opus 4.8 if you've got something really hard.
But for all of the tedious stuff, you should be using local models
where you just have to pay for the electricity, in my opinion.
Now, the very last thing I'll say
is that I'm intrigued by this idea of building a self improving business.
At the bottom layer, you've got a self improving code base,
which is what you can kind of already do here
by putting software issues into a Kanban board.
If you then plug that into agents that deal with product
and support roles, then you can start automatically
improving the product based on user feedback.
And then if you also add agents that can do
sales and marketing and finance and legal things, as well as kind of
the founder level stuff of like what's the hypothesis, what's
what's what's the direction of the market and so on.
Then all of this is with humans in the loop.
But you can start like going a lot faster
with fewer people than you could before, which was really interesting.
And so the very last thing I'll show you is we also use this to log into LinkedIn.
And it's fun because you're collaborating with the agent.
And so the agent can be like, oh, can you do two factor author, please?
Now LinkedIn thinks I'm a human and I kind of am.
I'm a human.
That's like using an agent,
kind of like a mechanical suit, to do
a lot more LinkedIn outreach than I would normally have the patience for.
And so I got it to build me a list of 200 people
I wanted to reach out to
when I was visiting the Bay area recently, and I actually got
a bunch of good meetings.
I wouldn't have had the patience to do that by hand,
so it's a pretty useful coming up to time.
So just to recap, we've looked at the design space of systems that run agents.
I hope that this has provided some useful ideas.
Talked about local versus centralized.
Obviously my opinion is that we should go centralized.
My opinion is that we still need an IDE task.
Scaling seems to be the most appropriate place to start,
but I think the org shapes are interesting.
Spec-driven development is a must make things mobile multiplayer.
Get your dev environment set up sorted.
Think about how you can reduce token costs, because if it's not hurting
now, it's going to be hurting soon.
And also think about how you can apply this beyond software engineering.
So thank you very much. That's me.
If you'd like help doing some of this then please reach out to me.
That's my LinkedIn.
Or if you'd just like to compare notes, I'd love to chat.
So thank you so much. Incredible luck.
Thank you very much.
Do we have any questions from anybody?
Oh, we've got two so far.
Lovely assistant.
Could get the mic and run it down for you.
We've got one this side and one this side.
Do you just raise your hand again?
Okay.
Thank you.
Cool.
Hello? Yes.
All right. Yeah.
That was a really, really cool talk.
And yeah, I think one of the things that
I was interested in is the kind of security aspect.
So obviously agents can do lots of things
and you just let it log into your LinkedIn and play around in there. Yes.
What have you got any guardrails and security things in there and to what?
To what extent have you got it there?
Because I find one of the hard things is letting agents run wild
versus making them secure, but then having to have lots of input manually.
So yeah.
Well, I think my first argument there is
that we're already doing better than like open floor on your on your Mac mini.
When I saw the open claw one password extension I was like.
So by just
logging into one website, it's only got one login.
It can't go and log into everything else. So that's step one.
And then you can also configure on a per project basis what MCP servers you expose.
But I think there is definitely a need for
and I think Ivan's working on something interesting in this space.
Like I definitely need for tooling that helps
you lock down what you're what you're giving permission to and what you're not.
It's not something
we necessarily want to try and bite off as well.
I think we'd rather partner with people
who are doing good things in that space, but it's definitely a need.
And the more people who ask me for like a governance for their agent control
plane, I'm like, oh, we need to put a governance panel in our thing.
So yes, definitely.
Thank you.
I'm just really.
Curious about how like what sort of structure you're running the GUI VMs.
Like how how's that working?
Because I'm quite fascinated. Yeah.
So it's pretty interesting.
The.
The way it works is that we run mutter,
which is the gnome compositor
inside a Docker container and, well, a Docker container.
And then we use a stream of plugins to we actually.
So there's this project called Wolf that does this for the gaming community
that is written in C++.
And for a long time they tried to use that.
And then we found it.
Honestly, I got really bored
of trying to write C++ and it was pretty flaky.
It ran the whole thing in, in like
one process for all of the different containers.
So when it crashed, it brought everything down.
So we ended up just taking the core pieces of that,
which is this rust plugin for handling Nvidia Cuda stuff in particular.
And this is all on our GitHub if you want to go and have a look.
But yeah, also feel free to ping me on.
I can tell you more about it. Great.
I think we've got one more question just here.
Thanks.
That was great.
You talked about still wanting an. IDE
early on.
What do you find you want to do with that?
I'm assuming that it doesn't need to look like
VS code from 2020.
So. So can you say a bit about what what it does look like?
Yeah.
I mean we just embedded Zed, which is a really nice idea
written in rust that I like because it's fast.
And also when you're running
hundreds of these things on a machine,
you care about the memory, use the memory footprint more.
I really like just being able
to watch the agent zip around between different files.
And also I find that watching
like a follow of the agent doing the work,
just sort of you ambient
absorb more knowledge about the code base
as it's doing that versus the black box that is Claude code these days.
And and then when something gets difficult
and the agent actually needs help, then you've already got a decent IDE
that you can search for things and, and look around.
So my take is you need an IDE on the inside,
but you also need the meta IDE, which is like the control plane for all
of the different agents you've got running and the higher level view of them.
I think we're at time.
You are at time. Thank you very much.
Please give it up for love.
Give us. Great. So